<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>The tie in measure 20</title>
    <meta http-equiv="Content-Type"
	  content="application/xhtml+xml;charset=UTF-8"/>
  </head>
<body>

  <p>I have a database where there are some interesting idref/xml:id pairs. It
  is also an example of a small but fairly complex problem that requires
  mature set of tools to solve.</p>

  <p>This is in the realm of critical edition of sheet music, i.e. I'm working
  with Music Encoding Initiative (MEI, http://music-encoding.org/home) and the
  music in question is Kaleidakustikon by Friedrich Kuhlau (1786 – 1832), an
  early piece of aleatoric music.  It is meant as a piece of musical
  recreation for piano players. The music consists of 21 piles (designated a
  to v excluding j) of 11 cards numbered 2 to 12 such that you can select one
  card from each pile by rolling a pair of dices. We, Royal Library, owns one
  copy and the only other known extant copy was sold in an auction in Paris a
  few years ago. Musikalisches Würfelspiel is a similar composition allegedly
  by Mozart (http://sunsite.univie.ac.at/Mozart/dice/)</p>

  <p>What we are up to is preparing a digital critical edition allowing users
  to get random music in svg/pdf/midi/mp3. I.e., you should get music both for
  your music stand and your ear.</p>

  <p>In order to do this I have encoded all the layers as complete piano
  tunes. The cards become MEI sections having xml:ids from a.2 to v.12. In
  order to simplify proofreading (and proof listening), I encode each layer as
  a complete tune. The tunes are stored in a native xml database and using
  xquery I can create a new pieces of music representing 21 rolls, one for
  each pile. Each selection of cards have an URI. There are (I presume) more
  music in that database than there are stars in the universe. If you start
  playing at big bang you'll not be ready at big crunch. The MEI generated can
  then be transformed into lilypond using xslt, which in turn can deliver SVG,
  MIDI or PDF (or PS) and using timidity (a sequencer) and an appropriate
  sound fond I can then get MP3.</p>

  <p>Sorry about the long prelude. And now we approaching the problem I wanted
  to tell you about. In one combination of cards there is a tie between two
  notes across a measure. Ties are "bows" connecting notes which the player
  should hold for a certain time. In MEI</p>

  <pre>
 &lt;section xml:id="s.7" type="C">
	    &lt;measure n="20">
	      &lt;dir staff="1" tstamp="1" place="above">s.7&lt;/dir>
	      &lt;staff n="1">
		&lt;layer>
		  &lt;beam>
		    &lt;note pname="f" oct="5" dur="8" stem.dir="down" />
		    &lt;note pname="e" oct="5" dur="8" stem.dir="down" />
		    &lt;note pname="c" oct="5" dur="8" stem.dir="down" />
		    &lt;note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8" stem.dir="down" />
		  &lt;/beam>
		  &lt;note pname="f" 
			oct="4" 
			dur="4" 
			stem.dir="up" 
			xml:id="s7tiestart" tie="m"  />
		  &lt;tie startid="s7tiestart" 
		       endid="globalCardTTieTargetXmlId" 
		       staff="1" curvedir="below"  />
		&lt;/layer>
  </pre>
</body>
</html>
